#### Date of Birth:

Aug 5, 1984

#### Home address:

Flat 13-E, Neelum Block, Gulshan-i-Jinnah, F-5/1 Islamabad Islamabad Pakistan

#### Phone:

+92.51.2874577

+92.321.5693421

### Zulfigar Shaikh

#### zulfigar.shaikh@gmail.com

**CAREER OBJECTIVE** 

Having completed my education from the most prestigious institutes in the world and gained an excellent quality experience in development and policy sectors in Pakistan, working with international organizations, government, and NGOs; I seek to contribute my knowledge and skills in an organization which contributes towards social and economic development.

#### **EDUCATION AND QUALIFICATIONS**

#### Cornell University, USA

2009

(Fulbright Scholar, United States Education Foundation)
Masters of Professional Studies (MPS) in International Development

#### Lahore University of Management Sciences (LUMS)

2006

B.Sc. (Hons) Economics

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### Pakistan Poverty Alleviation Fund (PPAF), Islamabad Credit and Enterprise Development Unit

Management Executive

Jul 2009 – till date

- Facilitating the Partner Organizations of PPAF for in development of their credit and enterprise operations aimed towards mobilizing community and reducing poverty.
- Extending relevant training and skill development services for staff and community to bolster their entrepreneurship skills and linking it with creating new and strengthening existing enterprises
- Ensuring smooth operations of Micro-credit and effective utilization of augmented Capacity Building grants (for MC support) under facilities from various donors including the World Bank, IFAD, USAID
- Working towards establishing and nurturing young partner organizations under Microfinance Innovation and Outreach Program (MIOP), International Linkage Partners Initiative (ILPI), Young partners Development Initiative (YPDI)
- Managing portfolio of projects under Enterprise Development Facility (EDF) and Program for Increasing Sustainable Microfinance (PRISM).
   Under PRISM, establishing links between MFIs and commercial sector.
- Evaluating and monitoring (including field monitoring) the operations, procedures, policies, sustainability and future strategy of Partner Organizations of PPAF and assessing their grass-root level clients.
- Organized and attended workshops to implement the guidelines from the donors and government of Pakistan

## Economic Affairs Division, Government of Pakistan, Islamabad, Pakistan World Bank's Capacity Building Project

Research Analyst

Jul 2006 - August 2007

 Analyzed and evaluated donor-funded projects, program strategies and government policy on thematic areas of poverty reduction, equitable economic development, employment generation, enterprise development in youth, esp. females

- Worked on aid coordination and providing policy input on improving effectiveness of Official Development Assistance (ODA)
- Evaluation and recommendation on Area Development Projects of Asian Development Bank (ADB)'s portfolio in Pakistan
- Appraisals for federal-level normal and mega projects, using statistical analysis, within the framework of government's Poverty Reduction Strategy Papers (PRSP), Medium Term Development Frameworks (MTDF), and Millennium Development Goals (MDGs) targets for Pakistan
- Liaison with bilateral and multilateral donors, implementing government agencies, and diverse local and international NGOs
- Appraisals for federal-level, and mega projects, using statistical analysis, and within the framework of government's Medium Term Development Frameworks (MTDF), and MDGs Targets for Pakistan
- Designed and managed international conferences

# **Lahore University of Management Sciences, Lahore, Pakistan** *Teaching Assistant*Jun 2006 – Jul 2006

- Coached and trained two hundred students of the National Outreach Program in verbal skills
- Assisted the program management in reporting through streamlining the information systems of the student records

#### LUMS Volunteer Society, Lahore, Pakistan

President

June 2005 - May 2006

- Initiated, managed and delivered various community service projects for various external stakeholders
- Strengthened and established new collaborations with other development organizations (NGOs/INGOs) with common goals
- Started training and vocational education programs for student and LUMS staff. Extended collaboration with LUMS Entrepreneurship Society (LES) to initiate joint enterprise ventures for student and external community, augmented by training and skill development
- Represented the student community and advocated their interests to the university management

#### National Commission for Human Development, Islamabad, Pakistan Intern June 2005 - May 2005

- Assessment and evaluation of projects and assistance to Director of education department
- Field visits to the district offices and projects of Mansehra

 Reported the results of the field visits with analysis of the on-going projects for the delivery mechanisms

#### Collective for Social Science Research, Karachi, Pakistan

Field Research Consultant

August 2005 - October 2005

- Conducted detailed field surveys on political, social and economic dynamics in Thatta, Sindh
- Analyzed survey results gathers during field visits
- Wrote reports and support material for the organization

### Devolution Trust for Community Empowerment, UN-nex Project, Islamabad, Pakistan

Research Assistant

June 2004 - August 2004

- Assisted in research work to the Chief Technical Advisor on governance issues
- Analyzed the effectiveness of Citizen Community Boards (CCBs) establishment process
- Assessing the performance of social and community projects

#### **PROJECTS**

**Tuzla Summer Institute, Bosnia -** Completed Under: Cornell University May 2008

- Role: Project Program Officer
- Project Description: The Head of Cornell Institute of Public Administration established a group of consultants. The team planned, designed and executed a full scale capacity building project on sustainable basis for the Youth of Tuzla, Bosnia. The group also secured funding and designed its modes through key partners including USAID.

**Devolution Support Project -** Completed Under: Lahore University of Management Sciences

July 2004 - January 2006

- Designed detailed surveys for assessing the economic political and social environment of the districts under study
- Conducted survey in the field for various villages of district
- Performed statistical analysis and comparative study on the effectiveness of newly established local government systems

**Project for Supporting LUMS Support Staff -** Completed Under: Lahore University of Management Sciences October 2004 - May 2005

- Role: Project Manager
- Initiated and managed Adult literacy and training program for support

#### staff of LUMS which included janitorial and security staff

#### ADDITIONAL SKILLS AND EXPERIENCE

Geographic Information Systems (GIS) Econometrics software: SPSS, STATA

Excellent Microsoft Office Suite Excellent Communication Skills

**Languages:** Proficient in English, Urdu, Sindhi, Punjabi Good understanding of Siraiki, and Arabic

#### CONFERENCES/SEMINARS

#### 3<sup>rd</sup> International Conference on Microfinance, Country Forum(Nov'09)

- Significant factors effecting the MF sector in Pakistan and untapped potential in the sector, especially savings and insurance
- Critical factors responsible for a recent severe crisis in MF sector in Pakistan
- Strategies and new developments on Micro-insurance programs, Mobile Banking, and Financial services for unbanked poor in Pakistan

# Environmental and Social Management Framework (ESMF) PPAF-Workshop (Oct '09)

- Learned the core need and requirement for establishing, enforcing ESMF
- Incorporating ESMF guidelines in operations and procedures of PPAF partners

Environmental and Social Seminar of Poverty Policy and Practice for South Asian Government Officials, Beijing, China (June 2007) Organized by International Poverty Reduction Centre, China

#### Pakistan Development Forum (April 2007)

- Part of the core organizing team
- Designed and managed the program for this international forum
- Closely coordinated with the key note speakers and dignitaries

#### International Visitors Leadership Program (IVLP) (Sep-Oct 2004)

- Selected and participated in this prestigious United States State Department sponsored program
- Meetings with many public-office holders, legislatures, academics, young business community leaders, and student and community leaders
- Travelling vastly all over the US (4 states) to understand the culture and exchange ours while having formal and informal meetings